hey bre and ter here going to show a
quick video on the Ecentric
accentuated uh ABM crunch um you can
also use a Swiss ball this is an ABM
it's just uh you know it just allows for
a little bit extra range of motion which
I like and uh there's a lot of different
reasons why you would want to do this
but it's important to have good core
stability but if you're you know say a
football player rugby player you collide
with
someone you're going to be pushed back
you want good core stability but you
also want good Ecentric strength so you
don't you know go in so you can limit
the amount of spinal hyperextension that
you go into so the rectus abdominis not
only uh keeps the co it prevents the
trunk from
hyperextending but it also you know
produces spinal flexion and controls
spinal extension so in sports it's not
always this nice neat thing where we
always stay stable we you go into
different ranges and it's my opinion
that you need good concentric Ecentric
and isometric strength but when dealing
with the lumbar spine you don't want to
go to end range so this is what I like
about I'm going to film this from the
side view so you can show you need to
learn how to control the different
segments of the spine and uh I was doing
bench press a while back and I got up I
racked the bar and I went to sit up and
I was like God that was hard I don't
remember this being very hard I think we
should be in good shape with every type
of movement and uh this is a lot of
people will will get down and do
crunches like this and they'll do you
know 200 crunches like this and that
doesn't that's that's why they think
crunches are so easy but when you do
them this way I'll show you I can barely
get 15 of these without them really
burning so this is actually a very
challenging just body weight exercise
especially if you're big like me so I'm
going to show you here okay this rests
under my lumbar spine and now as you can
see most of my motion here is at the
thoracic spine I'm not moving my lumbar
spine much so I'm going to show you here
Ecentric accentuated so I come up to
about 30° of trunk flexion I come down
slowly
up down slowly
I don't know if you can tell but I'm
shaking right
now and I'm getting a nice stretch down
here because I'm going uh I'm increasing
my range of
motion anyway that's all I don't even
know how many that was 10 my abs are
burning so bad right now I can't even
believe it so that's a very challenging
exercise if you do it nice and slow and
controlled like that you can do it with
a Swiss ball if you have an abmat do it
with an abmat but the keys to this were
I controlled my lumbar range of motion I
didn't move much at my lumbar spine it
was mostly at the thoracic spine and I
held the top for a second and then I
lowered slowly if you try this I bet you
20 reps will be very very challenging